听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们已经讨论了线性一致性
So, we've talked about linearizability
这是分布式系统可能的一个一致性模型
as one possible consistency model for distributed systems,
这是一个非常强的一致性模型
which is a very strong consistency model.
我前面讲过 线性一致性模型拥有一个非常吸引人的性质
And we said it has the very appealing property that
此模型让分布式系统看起来就像是没有副本一样
it actually makes a replicated system look as if it were not replicated.
此让系统看起来像是只有单一数据副本
It looks as if there was only a single copy of the data,
所有的操作都满足原子性
and all of the operations on it are atomic,
这使得线性一致性模型成为了一个非常易于使用的一致性模型
which makes linearizability a very easy-to-use consistency model.
你基本上不需要再考虑系统是否是分布式的了
You basically don't have to think about the fact that your system is distributed,
系统会按照你所期望的那样运作
and it just kind of works in the way you might expect.
不幸的是 这是有代价的
Unfortunately, it comes at a price as well.
线性一致性模型并不能适用于所有可能的情况
So, linearizability is not actually suitable in all possible circumstances
原因如下
for several reasons.
一种可能的原因是 实现此模型的代价非常大
One possible reason is that it's actually quite expensive to implement.
观察一下我们前面讨论的协议
If you look at the protocols that we discussed,
会发现协议会来回传输大量的消息 协议会涉及大量的等待响应步骤
there are lots of messages going back and forth, lots of waiting for responses,
大多数响应都需要两轮往返通信
probably something like two round trips for most requests.
因此 协议性能有一点慢
So, it's just going to be a bit slow basically.
另一个限制是
Another limitation is the scalability
系统的扩展性可能依赖于你所使用的具体算法
potentially depends a bit on the exact algorithm you're using.
举例来说 如果你使用类似Raft的共识算法
But if you're using a consensus algorithm like Raft, for example,
则所有更新操作都必须经过主节点排序
all of the updates have to be sequenced through the leader.
也就是说 所有的更新操作都会流经某个单一节点
So, there's a single node that all of the updates have to flow through.
因此 此类系统的扩展性受到单一节点能力的限制
And so, you are limited by the capacity of that one node in this kind of system.
也就是说 单一主节点会成为瓶颈
That one leader node can become a bottleneck.
进一步深入考虑此问题 就会发现
And what is perhaps the most the deepest problem
线性一致性和类似的强一致性模型
with linearizability and such strong consistency models,
都面临可用性问题
is problems with availability,
执行任何操作都需要与quorum节点联系
and that is, every operation that you do needs to contact a quorum of nodes.
这意味着如果你由于任何原因无法与quorum节点联系
And that means if you can't contact a quorum of nodes for whatever reason,
例如你的网络中断了 或者由于其他什么原因
maybe you're disconnected on the network, or so,
则你就无法处理任何操作
you can't process any operations.
如果无法与quorum节点联系 你就无法执行任何读或写操作
Neither reading nor writing is possible if you can't contact a quorum of nodes.
这也是人们提出替代一致性模型的原因
And that's why alternative consistency models have been developed,
这些一致性模型会在不同层面进行权衡
which have different trade-offs,
让某些方面变得更好一些 同时某些方面会更差一些
which are better in some regards and worse in other regards.
我们在本节要学习其中一个替代一致性模型 称为最终一致性模型
And the one that we will look at in this section is called eventual consistency.
我们用日历应用来举个例子
As an example, let's consider a calendar app.
屏幕左侧是在我计算机上运行的日历应用
So, here I have on the left-hand side, the calendar app running on my computer,
屏幕右侧是在我手机上运行的日历应用
and on the right-hand side, the calendar app running on my phone.
相信大家都了解日历应用的功能
And you all know how this works.
我可以在左侧添加一个事项 如分布式系统课程（Distributed systems lecture）
I can add an event on the left-hand side, say, Distributed systems lecture.
几秒钟后 这个事项会被同步到右侧的手机日历应用上
And this will sync within a couple of seconds over to the phone on the right-hand side.
随后 手机日历应用上应该会出现相同的事项
So, then, the same event should appear there.
出现了
Here we go.
类似地 我可以在手机上添加一个事项
And similarly, I can add an event on the phone.
这个事项也会被同步到我的计算机上
And this should sync over to the computer.
如果你仔细想想 就会发现我们拥有的是一个复制系统
Now, what we've got here, if you think about it, is a replicated system.
我的计算机上有一份日历的拷贝
We've got a copy of the calendar on my computer
我的手机上有一份日历的拷贝
and another copy of the calendar on my phone.
这两个副本是相互独立的
And these two replicas are independent from each other
证明这一点的方法是 我可以把我的手机调节成飞行模式
in the sense that I can put my phone into airplane mode,
从而阻止两个设备
and now I have prevented any communication
通过任何方式进行通信
between these two devices from happening.
举例来说 我可以在我的计算机上
And so, I could, for example, on my computer now,
把分布式系统课程的时间改成上午10:00
change the time of the Distributed systems lecture to 10:00 am.
修改并不会被同步到我的手机上 因为我的手机无法与外界通信
And this won't sync over to my phone, because my phone is unable to communicate.
我在手机上把事件标题改为分布式系统第1课（Distributed systems lecture 1）
And let's say on my phone, I change the title to, say, Distributed systems lecture 1.
截至最终关闭飞行模式之前 修改也不会被同步到我的计算机上
And this also won't sync back to the computer until I eventually turn off airplane mode.
现在 我关闭了飞行模式
And so, now, after airplane mode is off,
两个设备现在可以再次相互同步
now the two devices should be able to sync up with each other again.
一台设备上的修改结果应该会被传播到另一台设备上
And the changes from one should propagate over to the other.
你可以看到 现在发生的情况是
So, you can see what has happened now is
两个设备的事项发生事件都变为了上午10:00
the time of this event has moved to 10:00 am on both devices,
但标题“分布式系统课程”改成“分布式系统第1课”
but my change, changing the title Distributed systems lecture, I changed it to lecture 1,
这一标题修改结果不知何故从设备上消失了
but that change of the title has somehow disappeared.
我们这里遇到了冲突
And so, what we have here is a conflict,
因为我在两个不同的设备上并发修改了同一个日历事项
because I concurrently edited the same calendar event on two different devices
而两个设备在修改时处于断开连接的状态
while they were disconnected from each other.
当发生冲突时 我们需要解决冲突
And we had a conflict resolution that had to happen here.
很明显 我的日历应用在这里使用了“最后写入胜利”的解决方法
And what my calendar app did apparently was a last-writer-wins resolution,
在这种情况下 把时间更新为上午10:00的操作优先级
in which case, in this case, the update of the time to 10:00 am
在某种程度上高于更新标题操作的优先级
somehow took precedence over the update of the title.
因此 更新标题的操作被丢弃了
And so, the update of the title was discarded
更新时间的操作在两个设备上均生效
while the update of the time took effect on both devices.
因此 即使这里丢失了部分数据
So, even though some data was lost here,
但我们至少保证两个设备最终处于一致的状态
but at least we did end up with both devices being in a consistent state eventually.
诸如日历应用这样的系统
These systems, such like the calendar app,
可以用分布式系统中的CAP定理来形式化描述
can be formalized using this result from distributed systems called the CAP theorem.
CAP定理背后的基本思想非常简单
And this idea behind this is fairly simple.
你有一个存在网络分区的系统
It is, say, you have a system in which there's a network partition,
也就是说
that is,
一个子集的节点无法与另一个子集的节点通信
one subset of the nodes is unable to communicate with some other subset of the nodes.
在这种情况下 我们需要做出一个选择
In this case, we have to make a choice,
我们可以继续提供线性一致性
either we can continue providing linearizability,
但一部分节点可能无法处理请求
but some of the nodes won't be able to process requests,
我们也可以在不与quorum联系的条件下处理请求和操作
or we allow requests and operations to continue without contacting a quorum,
但这种情况下 我们有违反线性一致性的风险
but in that case, we risk violating linearizability.
在存在网络分区时 我们必须做出一个选择
And so, we have to just make this choice in the presence of a network partition.
这里有个演示
Illustrated here.
左侧是隔离节点A和B 它们形成了一个quorum
So, we've got on the left-hand side of the partition nodes A and B, which form a quorum,
它们可以继续为操作提供满足线性一致性的服务
and they can continue providing a linearizable service for these operations.
但右侧的节点C陷入了两难的困境
But node C here on the right-hand side is stuck in this dilemma,
因为节点C
because either the node C
或者必须等待网络分区被修复 使它能够与quorum通信
has to wait for this network partition to be healed before it can reach a quorum,
这可能需要无限长的事件
which might take indefinite amount of time.
在这个时间段内
And so, during that time,
节点C实际上是不可用的 无法处理任何请求
node C is effectively unavailable, and not able to process any requests.
节点C也可以使用本地状态继续处理请求
Or node C just goes ahead and uses its local state,
但在这种情况下 节点C无法知道A写入了v_1
but in that case, it won't know about the value v_1 that was written by A.
因此 我们在这种情况下会违反线性一致性
So, in this case, we will have violated linearizability.
当系统可能出现网络分区时
And so, this is just a fundamental choice that you have to make
我们必须要做出一个选择
in a system in which network partitions might occur.
最终一致性
And eventual consistency
是人们经常使用的另一类一致性模型
is sort of the broad category of consistency models that typically people move to
当不想假设节点能随时与quorum通信时
if they don't want to make an assumption of
就可以使用最终一致性模型
being able to communicate with a quorum, something like that.
如果我们想让每个副本都有能力基于本地状态处理操作
So, if we want each replica to be able to process operations just based on its local state
处理操作时不需要等待quorum的响应
and without waiting for a communication with a quorum,
那我们就无法满足线性一致性 但我们可以满足较弱的一致性模型
we cannot achieve linearizability, but we can achieve weaker consistency models.
最终一致性模型一般按照下述方法定义
And the way eventual consistency is usually defined is like this.
首先 一个副本可以基于本地状态处理任意读请求
First of all, any read requests, a replica can just process based on its local state.
随后 每当一个副本应用了某个更新
And then, whenever some updates get applied to one replica,
它们最终会在某个时刻将更新漫游到其他副本上
they will eventually wander over the network at some point to other replicas.
我们想要保证的是
And what we want to guarantee is that
如果我们假设在某个时刻更新能够停止
if we assume that at some point the updates stop,
则在更新停止后
then eventually after the updates have stopped,
所有副本最终可以处于相同的状态
then all of the replicas end up in the same state.
这么定义没问题 但这是一个相当弱的一致性模型
Now, this is OK, but it's a fairly weak property,
举例来说 如果更新永远不会停止呢？
because, for example, what if the updates never stop?
可能存在一个更新或处理过程永远不会停止的系统
You could have a system in which continually updates or process, non-stop.
最终一致性没有定义这种情况下会发生什么
And so, in this case, eventual consistency does not define what will happen in that case,
因为这种情况不满足最终一致性的前提条件
because the premise of the statement of this definition is not true.
因此 人们所做的是
So, what people have done is
定义一种比最终一致性稍强的一致性定义
to define an alternative slight strengthening of eventual consistency
称为强最终一致性
called strong eventual consistency,
此一致性模型额外定义了两个性质
which is defined with two properties.
第一个性质是 任意作用在一个副本上的更新操作
So, first of all, we say that any update that has been made on one replica
最终一定也会作用在另一个副本上
will eventually also be made on another replica.
也就是说 更新操作会散布到整个网络中
So, updates get disseminated over the network.
我们不保证更新操作需要花多长时间才能散布到其他节点
We don't make any guarantees about how long that's going to take.
我们只是说最终会散布完毕
We just say eventually this will happen.
第二个性质是
And secondly,
当两个副本处理的更新操作所构成的集合相同
whenever you have two replicas that have processed the same set of updates,
则这两个副本必须具有相同的状态
then those replicas must be in the same state,
对于任意读请求 它们必须返回相同的结果
and thus, they will return the same results to any read requests.
即使这些更新操作
And this must hold
实际上是在不同副本按照不同的顺序应用的 此性质也必须得到满足
even if those updates were actually applied in a different order on different replicas.
因此 这就回到
And so, this comes back down to
我们前面介绍的因果关系广播复制协议了
the causal broadcast-based replication protocols that we saw earlier, for example,
当状态操作函数满足交换律时
where if you have commutative operations for operating the state,
就可以让不同副本按照不同的顺序应用更新操作
then you can have different replicas updating the state in a different order,
且保证副本都会收敛到相同的最终状态
and still converging to the same final state.
这个收敛思想
And so, this idea of convergence
是满足最终一致性和强最终一致性的关键
is really at the core of eventual consistency and strong eventual consistency.
最终一致性和强最终一致性
Now, both eventual consistency and strong eventual consistency
都具有非常好的性质
have some very nice properties.
如果你基于这个模型实现协议
If you want to implement this model,
则一个副本在执行操作时就不需要与其他副本通信了
there is no need ever for an operation to wait for communication with another replica.
一个副本总能处理操作请求
So, a replica can always process operations.
读操作和写操作都可以在本地完成处理
Both reads and writes can be processed just locally
无需等待任何通信
without waiting for any communication.
当然了 有时后台还是会不可避免地进行一些通信
Of course, eventually, sometime communication will have to happen in the background,
但操作过程无需等待任何通信
but the operations don't have to wait for it,
这意味着操作处理过程总会非常迅速
which means that the operations can always be fast.
操作过程永远不涉及往返通信
They're never waiting for network round trips.
同时 操作过程总是可靠的
And the operations can always be reliable,
因为即使出现网络中断
because even if the network is interrupted,
副本仍然可以继续处理操作
and a replica can continue processing operations.
我们可以使用
And we can use these broadcast protocols of
因果关系广播、FIFO广播、或其他弱广播协议
causal broadcast or FIFO broadcast or these other weaker broadcasts
来让一个副本向其他副本分发更新操作
as a way of distributing the updates from one replica to another.
最终一致性系统可能会面临的一个问题是
Now, one problem that can arise with eventually consistent systems is that
多个副本可能会同时并发更新同一个对象或同一个数据项
the same object or the same data item can be concurrently updated by multiple replicas.
无法阻止此类情况的发生
And there's nothing stopping this of course,
因为多个副本在更新时不需要通信
because they cannot communicate necessarily.
由于我们会并发更新相同的对象
And so, because we have these concurrent updates of the same object,
我们可能会遇到冲突
we might have conflicts.
必须用一些方法来解决冲突问题
And so, those conflicts will have to be resolved in some way or another.
我们在日历应用中看到的解决方法是最后写入方胜利策略
With the calendar app, what we saw is just the last-writer-wins policy,
即如果一个更新操作在另一个更新操作之后
where one of the updates took precedence over the other,
则较早的更新操作就被丢弃了
the other one was just discarded.
我们还可以设计更复杂的冲突解决策略
But we can also devise more sophisticated conflict resolution policies.
我在这个领域做了一些合并算法的研究
And I've actually done some research in this area on merge algorithms,
基本方法是设计适合并发更新操作的数据结构
which will take concurrently updated data structures
并把结果合并到一起 得到清晰的最终状态 以解决冲突问题
and merge them together into a clean final state to resolve the conflict.
这就是最终一致性的概念
So, that's eventual consistency.
我们现在回顾一下本节课讲解的一致性模型和算法
I'll now recap the consistency models and algorithms that we talked about in this lecture,
我们按照所需系统模型假设从强到弱的顺序
and do that in the order of how strong the assumptions are
依次回顾各个模型和算法
that they make about the system model.
这种不同算法的比较方法会比较有意义一些
This is an interesting way of comparing these different algorithms and approaches.
首先 我们从实现原子提交的两阶段提交开始
So, first of all, we started with atomic commitment as in two-phase commit.
回忆一下 原子提交的模型是
And remember that the model with atomic commit is that
只有当所有参与节点都投提交票 才可以提交某一事务
a transaction can commit only if all of the participating nodes vote to commit.
这意味着
And so, this means that
原子提交要求与所有参与节点进行通信 这是不可避免的
inevitably, atomic commit requires communicating with all participating nodes,
而某个事务的参与节点可能是系统中的所有节点
which might be all nodes in the system.
如果任意一个节点崩溃
So, if any one node is crashed,
原子提交就不能提交任何事务了
atomic commit will not be able to commit any transactions.
为了实现原子提交
So, this is a very strong assumption that we have to make
我们必须为系统通信设置非常强的假设
about the communication that happens in the system.
提交事务时 我们必须与所有节点通信并等待它们的响应
We have to communicate with all nodes and wait for their response.
进一步 我们必须假设部分同步系统模型
Moreover, we have to assume a partially synchronous system model,
因为我们在协议中必须设置超时机制和失效检查机制
because we have timeouts and failure detection that has to happen.
系统模型假设弱一级的是共识和全序关系广播
Now, one step down from this is consensus and total order broadcast.
FLP的结论告诉我们
And so, consensus and total order broadcast,
共识和全序关系广播也要求部分同步系统模型
the FLP result told us that this also requires a partially synchronous model.
FLP的结论称
So, the FLP result says that
不存在实现共识的异步网络模型算法
there's no asynchronous algorithm for implementing consensus.
因此 我们必须假设部分同步系统模型
And so, therefore, partial synchrony is what we have to assume.
但共识对于通信的假设要稍弱一些
But in terms of the communication, consensus actually assumes a bit less,
因为共识仅要求与quorum通信
because it only requires communication with a quorum.
因此 我们可以容忍少数节点不可用
And so, therefore, we can tolerate a minority of nodes being unavailable,
即使少数节点不可用 算法仍然可以正常处理请求
and the algorithm will still be able to make progress and complete as normal.
共识和全序关系广播都使用这一稍弱的通信假设
And so, this holds for consensus and total order broadcast,
我们前面讲过 这两种协议是等价的
which are equivalent to each other as we said.
进一步 我们学习了满足线性一致性的比较交换
Moreover, we saw that for linearizable compare-and-swap,
我们可以使用全序关系广播实现满足线性一致性的比较交换
we can implement that using total order broadcast.
实际上 可以证明
And in fact, it is possible to prove that
满足线性一致性的比较交换与共识是等价的
linearizable compare-and-swap is also equivalent to consensus.
这三个问题可以相互归约
So, all these three problems are actually reducible to each other.
它们都要求与quorum通信、都假设部分同步网络模型
They all have the property that they require a quorum and partial synchrony.
有趣的是 列表继续往下
Moving down in the list, interestingly,
满足线性一致性的get和set操作
a linearizable get and set operation
比满足线性一致性的比较交换操作要求的系统模型假设又弱一级
has weaker assumptions than a linearizable compare-and-swap operation,
因为我们可以使用前面介绍的ABD算法实现get和set操作
because for get and set, we can just use the approach we saw earlier, the ABD algorithm,
即使用quorum读和带读修复的quorum写来实现
which means quorum writes and quorum reads with read repair.
这仍然要求与quorum节点通信
And this still requires communicating with a quorum of nodes,
但请注意
but notice that
这个算法不需要计时器 不需要超时机制 不需要失效检查器
in this algorithm, there are no timers, there are no timeouts, there's no failure detection.
此算法是完全异步的 不需要引入任何时钟
The algorithm is actually completely asynchronous. It doesn't require on clocks at all.
因此 这意味着
And so, this means that
满足线性一致性的get和set操作
actually linearizable get and set
所要求的系统模型假设被比满足线性一致性的比较交换操作更弱
has weaker assumptions about the system model than compare-and-swap.
最后 我们一直向下移动到我们能做出的最弱假设
And finally, as we move all the way down to the weakest assumptions that we can make,
我们有了最终一致性
now we're with eventual consistency,
即每个副本都可以更新和读取自己的本地状态
where every replica can update and read its own local state
更新和读取时不需要等待来自其他任何副本的通信
without waiting for any communication with any other replica.
最终一致性的通信要求是最小的
So, the communication need is totally minimized here.
我们也不需要时间假设
And we still make no timing assumptions.
对于最终一致性和强一致性
So, this is about the weakest that we can assume
我们可以设置最弱的系统假设
for both eventual consistency and strong eventual consistency.
同样 对于广播协议
And also, in terms of the broadcast protocols,
即因果关系广播、FIFO广播、可靠广播和尽力广播来说
causal broadcast, FIFO broadcast, reliable broadcast and best-effort broadcast,
所有这些协议都满足的一个性质是 节点可以立刻给自己传递消息
all of these have the property that they can deliver a message to themselves immediately.
节点不需要等待来自其他任何节点的通信
A node doesn't have to wait for communication with any other node
就可以给自己传递消息
in order to deliver a message to itself.
因此 这些协议也满足的一个性质是 如果传递的消息是更新操作
And this thus also has the property that if these messages are updates,
则不需要等待任何通信即可在本地应用此更新操作
that means updates can be applied locally without waiting for any communication.
也就是说
So, this also has the property that
这些协议在处理本地更新操作时也不需要等待任何通信
no waiting for communication is required in order to process local updates.
这就是今天有关一致性模型的全部内容了
So, that's all on consistency models for today.